<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- output sample to be generated by application -->
<portfolio id="AuditLocalGovernmentDepartment1_2020" description="AAG Naser Arllati: supervision of Departments Auditing Local Government Institutions" coverage="year of 2020" org="National Audit Office of Kosovo" publish="1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="PortfolioSchema.xsd" >
	<audits>
	<Audit>
			<About id="GJILAN2019" year="2019" month="01">
				<version id="1.0"/>
				<title>
					<tx l="eng" nm="AUDIT ON THE ANNUAL FINANCIAL STATEMENTS OF GJILAN MUNICIPALITY "/>
				</title>
				<WorkingLanguage wl="eng"/>
			</About>
			<Background>
				<ak>Audit of Gjilan Municipality for 2019, which includes the Opinion of the Auditor General on Annual Financial Statements. Examination of 2019 financial statements was undertaken in accordance with the International Standards of Supreme Audit Institutions (ISSAIs).
</ak>
			</Background>
			<Scope>
				<ak>The Audit involves examination and evaluation of Financial Statements and other financial records in regard to as the following: 
•	Whether the financial statements give a true and fair view of the accounts and financial matters for the audit period;
•	Whether the financial records, systems and transactions comply with applicable laws and regulations; 
•	Whether the internal controls and internal audit functions are appropriate and efficient; and
•	Whether appropriate actions for implementation of audit recommendations have been undertaken
Particular importance should be paid to the property tax database management; procurement process during the contracts’ evaluation and implementation; misclassification of expenditures; recording of non-financial assets; operationalization of E-assets program; and undertaking actions to reduce liabilities and properly disclose them in the AFS. 
</ak>
			</Scope>
			<Cases>
				<Case nr="F20200516-204918" nm="Failure to impose property taxes and to update the taxpayers database, due to incorrect/incomplete information registration " eff="Erroneous zonal calculations, which affects the budget of revenues. " act="Law no.06/L-005 on Property Tax, Article 12 section 2.1" doc="" Include="Yes" number="1">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="01 Input Controls" issue="01 Adequate input validation controls"/>
					<quote type="description">The Law no.06/L-005 on Property Tax, Article 12 section 2.1 stipulates that the Municipality has the following responsibilities: registers and manages property tax data in the property tax registers as defined in the sub-legal act issued by the Ministry of Finance pursuant to paragraph 5 of Article 14 of this Law.
Were identified errors related to the information on taxpayers properties in the system which leads to incorrect calculations of tax burdens.
Entry control procedures should ensure that each transaction has been entered, processed and recorded completely and accurately. The information system should have clear validity checks for mandatory data attributes and communicating problems. 
</quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
				<Case nr="F20200516-210315" nm="In the Property Tax database there are shortcomings in controls of mandatory fiels and related error handling" eff="The lack of mandatory data attributes which should trow error messages, and lack of procedures for identifying errors and correcting them before processing, poses the risk of erroneal calculations" act="" doc="" Include="Yes" number="2">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="01 Input Controls" issue="03 Adequate procedures for error handling"/>
					<quote type="description">The Property Tax database  should have clear validity checks associated with core data attributes for error handling and communicating problems to operators. Errors that occur when placing data in the relevant fields should be tracked and corrected before completing transactions. </quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
				<Case nr="F20200516-212419" nm="Failure to register assets and incorrect recording of assets in “e- assets” system" eff="Overstatement/understatement of capital assets" act="Regulation 02/2013, Article 6, section 3 adn Article 13, section 2" doc="" Include="Yes" number="3">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="01 Input Controls" issue="01 Adequate input validation controls"/>
					<quote type="description">According to Regulation 02/2013 on Management of Non- financial Assets, Article 6, section 3, capital assets must be recorded in KFMIS, whilst non- capital assets and stocks in the “e- assets” system. Meanwhile, Article 13, section 2, regarding acquisition and construction of non-financial assets for other budgetary organisations stipulates that when non-financial assets have passed all the rules and procedures of delivery, the funding budget organisation will close the Ongoing Investment category.
The application must have validity control procedures during input operations to protect it against errors or incomplete data. They must be configured to ensure that application transactions are executed in accordance with the expected performance.</quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
				<Case nr="F20200516-213951" nm="Lack of of internal procedure on assets management and knowledge on the requirements of the Regulation on assets management" eff="Failure to register assets and incorrect recording of assets in “e- assets” system" act="Regulation 02/2013, Article 6, section 3" doc="" Include="Yes" number="4">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="01 Input Controls" issue="02 Management of source documents, data collection and entry"/>
					<quote type="description">According to Regulation 02/2013 on Management of Non- financial Assets, Article 6, section 3, assets under €1,000 should be recorded in the e-assets system. Whilst, according to Article 4, the Chief Administrative Officer is responsible for adoption of internal rules and procedures on recording, preservation and disposal of non-financial assets. 
The Municipality does not use e-assets program to record and manage the assets under €1,000. The Municipality applies the Excel program to record these assets. Assets are not recorded in this program by the item’s individual value, but by the value of the transaction incurred. Considering the possibility for data manipulation and because assets depreciation is not applied, the value of assets disclosed in the AFS is considered incorrect.
</quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
				<Case nr="F20200516-220113" nm="The Property Tax database exibits errors in the configuration of the values per square meters according to zones" eff="Inadequate system configuration Property Tax database risks irregularities in calculation of property tax revenues" act="Law no.06/L-005, Article 12 section 2.1" doc="" Include="Yes" number="5">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="02 Processing Controls" issue="02 Application controls"/>
					<quote type="description">The Law no.06/L-005 on Property Tax, Article 12 section 2.1 stipulates that the Municipality has the following responsibilities: registers and manages property tax data in the property tax registers as defined in the sub-legal act issued by the Ministry of Finance pursuant to paragraph 5 of Article 14 of this Law
The municipal regulation on immovable property tax for year 2019 determines the values per square meters according to zones. In five cases, we found that the calculation was not made according the requirements of the regulation:
•	The value of square meter for residential property in Zone I is €425, whilst in two tested cases it was calculated by €375. 
•	The value of square meter for residential property in Zone II is €340, whilst in two tested cases it was calculated by €325; and 
•	The value of square meter for unfinished properties is €146, whilst in one case it was calculated by €130. 
</quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
				<Case nr="F20200519-142824" nm="The Municipality uses a software to protocol the invoices, but without mechanism to validate its accuracy" eff="Failure to protocol invoices and delays in paying them " act="Financial Rule 01/2013, Article 24, section 1.3" doc="" Include="Yes" number="6">
					<cts source="AITAM" domain="07 Application Controls" area="04 Application security controls" issue="01 Traceability mechanisms"/>
					<quote type="description">According to Article 24, section 1.3 of the MoF Financial Rule 01/2013, the invoice should be protocolled and registered in the invoice book. Whilst, Article 37.1 stipulates that all invoices received by a budget organisation should be paid within 30 days unless otherwise stipulated in the contract. 
We found that 19 invoices were protocolled after they were paid, whilst 14 invoices were paid but they were not registered yet. The Municipality does not have an invoice book and uses a software to protocol the invoices, however there is no mechanism to validate its accuracy. Moreover, seven invoices in the amount of €10,059 were paid after the deadline of 30 days was due. The reason behind the delayed payment of invoices was the lack of budget.
</quote>
					<quote type="recommendation"/>
				</Case>
			</Cases>
			<Recommendations>
				<Recommendation nr="R20200516-220946" priority="Urgent" risk="Reputational" riskevaluation="Municipality" accepted="Yes" repeated="Yes" importance="Strategic" category="Policy on input validation, processing and errors" number="1">
					<quote type="description">The Mayor should ensure that identified errors related to the information on taxpayers properties in the system are corrected in order to enable as a realistic calculation of tax burdens as possible.</quote>
					<quote type="aplan"/>
					<quote type="responsible"/>
					<quote type="timeline"/>
					<quote type="outcome"/>
					<quote type="remarks"/>
					<findings>
						<finding nr="F20200516-204918"/>
						<finding nr="F20200516-210315"/>
						<finding nr="F20200516-220113"/>
					</findings>
					<!--<monitoring/>-->
				</Recommendation>
				<Recommendation nr="R20200516-221315" priority="Urgent" risk="Reputational" riskevaluation="State" accepted="Yes" repeated="No" importance="Strategic" category="Systems' compliance" number="2">
					<quote type="description">The Mayor should ensure that the purchased items are recorded in the respective assets registers according to the requirements of the Regulation on assets management. Assets purchased for Tregu enterprise should be written off the Municipality’s assets register</quote>
					<quote type="aplan"/>
					<quote type="responsible"/>
					<quote type="timeline"/>
					<quote type="outcome"/>
					<quote type="remarks"/>
					<findings>
						<finding nr="F20200516-212419"/>
					</findings>
					<!--<monitoring/>-->
				</Recommendation>
				<Recommendation nr="R20200516-222100" priority="Urgent" risk="Operational" riskevaluation="State" accepted="Yes" repeated="No" importance="Strategic" category="Policies and procedures" number="3">
					<quote type="description">The Mayor should ensure that the assets under €1,000 is recorded in the e-assets system as required in the applicable regulations. He should also approve internal rules and regulations on assets. </quote>
					<quote type="aplan"/>
					<quote type="responsible"/>
					<quote type="timeline"/>
					<quote type="outcome"/>
					<quote type="remarks"/>
					<findings>
						<finding nr="F20200516-213951"/>
					</findings>
					<!--<monitoring/>-->
				</Recommendation>
				<Recommendation nr="R20200519-143025" priority="Urgent" risk="Reputational" riskevaluation="Entity" accepted="Yes" repeated="No" importance="Strategic" category="Lack of Accuracy validation in invoices register" number="4">
					<quote type="description">Failure to protocol or delayed protocolling of received invoices leads to the risk of invoices being paid more than once and exceeding of the legal deadline for paying the liabilities may put the Municipality subject to lawsuits filed by economic operators thus leading to more court/bailiff related expenditures for the Municipality. </quote>
					<quote type="aplan"/>
					<quote type="responsible"/>
					<quote type="timeline"/>
					<quote type="outcome"/>
					<quote type="remarks"/>
					<findings>
						<finding nr="F20200519-142824"/>
					</findings>
					<!--<monitoring/>-->
				</Recommendation>
			</Recommendations>
		</Audit>
	</audits>
</portfolio>
